<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An honest commoner's speech</title>
            <author>Honest commoner.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12087396</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12087396</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44288)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 73:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An honest commoner's speech</title>
                  <author>Honest commoner.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:53772:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53772:1"/>
            <head>AN Honeſt Commoner's SPEECH.</head>
            <p>WHere the King ends his <hi>Speech,</hi> I will begin mine. Since his Majeſty himſelf tells us, <hi>That we have ſuch an opportunity now to ſettle the future Quiet and Proſperity of theſe Kingdoms, and all</hi> Europe, <hi>as we can never hope to ſee again:</hi> We ought, I think, to believe him, and apply it the beſt we can to a common Safety. Give me leave therefore to ſay and preſs you, by all that is dear to you; your Liberties, your Honour, your Poſterity, that having but one throw more for your Lives, for your All; you trifle not, you miſtake not, you miſuſe not this opportunity. <hi>Charity begins at home;</hi> it is a ſenſible Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, and never more ſeaſonable; and to inſtruct our ſelves the beſt we can, allow me to look back a little into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reigns.</p>
            <p>The ſtruggle that has been in theſe Kingdoms, ſince the latter end of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's Time, between the Court and Countrey Party, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, I am ſure it ought not, to be unknown to any Member that has the Honour of Sitting in Parliament; for nothing is more Inſtructive and Accompliſhing to the Perſons that compoſe it. We ſhall find an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the Court to grow upon the Rights and Priviledges of the People, and a moſt flattering Clergy ever rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſtamp all theſe Attempts, under the Banner of <hi>Prerogative,</hi> with their <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> I will not run into their Hiſtory, that of the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> ſhall prevent me; to be had at every Book-ſellers; there cannot be a worſe, nor a truer. It leads me to pity Kings, and excuſe them, for their Errors of their Government are rarely their own, they ſee and hear by other Mens Eyes and Ears; and as they are intereſted, Kings are abuſed, and Royal Authority diſhonourably employ'd. It has been the Endeavour as well as Duty of the Sovereign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of this Kingdom to give a check to theſe Abuſes, by repreſenting free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their Kings the Law, the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, what they may and may not do, what is his, and what is theirs, their Conſiſtency and Dependency, and the dangerous Conſequence of their adhering to ſuch Counſels, and perſiſting in thoſe Courſes. And to the Honour of the Conſtitution, and Wiſdom of our Parliaments, be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, thoſe Kings have left the faireſt Characters to their Names, that have lived beſt with their Parliaments; and you will find that they have been the ableſt and valianteſt of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that have ſeen them ofteneſt and followed their Advice moſt; but Three great opportunities we have loſt, which I will but hint at, that you may encreaſe your Zeal, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring them to improve this only one that is left us, by which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve the loſs of them, and ſave all.</p>
            <p>The Firſt was the Conceſſions of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. to the 19 Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons preſented to him in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> by the Parliament, 1647. which the K. himſelf aſſures us were not the Conſtraint, but Illumination of his Afflictions; for after a ſeries of Succeſſes againſt him, the Houſes only prayed their antient Rights of him, that though Perſonally in their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they deſired ever to be under his legal Authority, and al horred to be thought to have their King at their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53772:2"/>Mercy, but that they only redeemed him from the ill Counſel of Mercileſs and Mercenary Men. This opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was loſt by the interruption of their own victorious Army, which influenced by a few ſuperiour Officers, that found not their Account by the Peace, had always the Means and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to diſcontent their Followers againſt their Maſters, and ſo turned their Swords upon thoſe that paid them, and from that time fought for their Leaders, rather than their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; though in this the Men were poſſibly out-witted and abuſed. The ill Conſequences of this Overſight, or rather Violence, were many and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible. Firſt, That King's Tragical Death, not only a Diſhonour to the Nation, but a beheading of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; a prepoſterous diſabling of the Conſtitution, as well as an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Action. Secondly, From this ſprung new Wars with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all over this Kingdom, in <hi>Kent, Eſſex, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> eſpecially at <hi>Dunbar, Preſton,</hi> and <hi>Worceſter;</hi> and though the Veins that were opened a freſh upon this ſad occaſion; bled freely and largely every where, and put all parts of the Kingdom into Mourning, more periſhing in two Years of this ſecond Civil War, than in the ſeven Years of the firſt; yet the fataleſt part of the Buſineſs, was the Baniſhment of the young Princes; for when they were compelled to ſeek their Bread among Strangers, they learned their Cuſtoms, and ſuck'd in, with foreign Air, outlandiſh Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and this naturally led them to diſlike the Government, as well as the People of their own Countrey; which very conſideration has ſometimes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged me to make allowances in my own Reflections, upon the Conduct of the Brothers, who perhaps were more Unhappy than Faulty, and much of that owing to us our ſelves. I will cloſe this Remark with ſaying, We had ſaved our King, our Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, our Honour, our Blood, and Treaſure, and a better Thing, our Government, if we had improved that <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> opportunity. But ſome will ſay this was not the Act of the Kingdom, but of a few ambitious Men, true; but the Conſequences were as bad; and for that Reaſon let us have a care of <hi>Victorious Armies,</hi> and their <hi>Ambitious Leaders,</hi> while they are in our Power; there is, at leaſt, that Inſtruction in it. But our next Inſtance ſhall be of an opportunity as extravagantly loſt, and with a ſort of univerſal Neglect, if not Conſent; and that was the Reſtauration of his Son King <hi>Charles</hi> II. For he that would have Married <hi>Lambert</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and returned upon almoſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publican Principles, would certainly have thought it Duty and Religion to have ſubmitted to, and performed his Royal Father's Commiſſions to the Priviledges of the People, and Power of Parliaments; but this opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was ſlipt too; our Extreams were ſo great in Love and Hatred, that we could not find in our Hearts to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any mean for the real Good of Prince and People: We would be Debauch'd in ſpight to the preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Party we hated, and the King ſhould return unconditional, that we might be even with them for their Unmonarchical Principles. It was <hi>Rebellion</hi> now to fight by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority againſt his Perſon, and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to diſinguiſh his politick from his perſonal Capacity; and <hi>Parliaments</hi> themſelves might be Diſloyal, for we were told, <hi>That our Kings being Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns, they had no Superiour but God; and their People, neither Collectively, nor Repreſentatively, could ſo much as put the leaſt Reſtraint upon the Perſon of their King, and that ſuch Attempts were Treaſon within the</hi> 25 Ed. 3. and much more to alter the antient Frame of the Government. But about 66
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53772:2"/>being awakened out of our exceſſes of Joy and Revenge, by the nature of Things, we repented too late; and after 78 we would have given half our Eſtates, and as much of our Blood too, for ſuch an opportunity as what we had ſo prodigally and irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably loſt.</p>
            <p>This falſe Step we hop'd to retrieve by the Bill of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Abortive, as it deſerved; for it was purely Perſonal in its Regards, loving one Man more than Liberty, and hating another Man more than Slavery; and miſerable is that People, whoſe Security is more from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Magiſtrate, than the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government. The next greateſt opportunity of all, was at the <hi>Election</hi> of this King. He ſeems not to have come for a Crown, but our Safety; to ſecure the Succeſſion, rather than obtain the Poſſeſſion: Doubtleſs we ſurpriſed him with the tender of it, and as one unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt our Love, after he had overcome our Fears, he ſubmitted to the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of a Crown,</hi> to preſerve what he had procured for us; <hi>A Deliverance from our Jealouſies of Popery and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick Power.</hi> To do what we ſhould have done in thoſe former Occaſions, had been to ſave us indeed; but we loſt our Memory now in our Joys, as we had done before; I will not ſay our Wits, and leſs our Morals; but that we ſhould miſs of the beſt part of the End of our ſending for him, and his coming, has ſomething in it ſo reproachful to our Underſtandings or Integrity, that it is never to be wip'd off, but by improving this opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity now in our Hands, and which the King tells us is like to be the laſt: And ſince it may be the laſt time alſo that I may have the Honour of ſpeaking to you, at leaſt ſo ſolemnly, give me leave to uſe all the freedom of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Man, and take every Thing in good Part, as it is meant in the greateſt good Will; for whatever be the ſucceſs, I ſhall have the ſatisfaction of having clear'd my Conſcience; that if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of our Safety come hereafter to prove the means of our Deſtruction, the World and Poſterity ſhall know I had no hand in the Tragedy.</p>
            <p>That which I call the preſent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, is taking the advantage of the neceſſity of Affairs, to ſettle the Government upon its true Baſis, and ſupply whatever we find Defective. If this yet wants an Explanation, then, I ſay, <hi>Let us not give a Penny of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney till we are ſafe at home;</hi> let us be out of Danger from being the worſe for Victory; let us know what is ours, how we ſhall keep it, and what we have in future to truſt to. As the K. tells us, <hi>We muſt ſink under the great Power of</hi> France, if, in this Seſſion, we make not Proviſion for a vigorous Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>France;</hi> ſo I tell you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you ſecure your ſelves againſt the very ſucceſſes you hope for, your Proviſions may be the Means of your own Ruine inſtead of Safety. The King is a Stranger to our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and was nearer to the Crown in Blood, than to our Government in his Education. He is very able in Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Affairs, and the Civil too, of the Place he took his Breeding in, and has better knowledge in foreign Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs than we have; but in Engliſh Buſineſs it's no Diſhonour to him to be told his Relation to us, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, and what is fit for him to do; And who ſhould, or who can do it with that Freedom and Authority, that we may and ought to do? And the rather, becauſe we ſee how much he is influenced by ill or weak Men, that are the mere Creatures of Power; ſome ſtained in their Credit, or Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars; others Covetous, and that have ſeeond Broods to provide for; ſome Voluptuous and Prodigal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; a vaſt Number of <hi>Foreigners,</hi> that wait both for Fortunes and Title upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53772:3"/>of this War; enough to move a Conquerour to ask or take more Power, than is for the ſafety of our Conſtitution to ſuffer. I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that I have read, <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Story; what he did with his victorious Army when he returned home, and have ſeen ſomething to the ſame purpoſe in our own Countrey. The World has very few <hi>Solons, Dyons,</hi> and <hi>Scipios</hi> in it; and to be very free with you, as the Time and Caſe obliges me, there are ſome Paſſages, I have obſerved, ſince the Revolution with no little regret; the Imployment of unpopular and ungrateful Men; the laying by the moſt zealous Men in the Change, and as able as any Body to ſerve; the Preſſing in the Houſe by Miniſters; the interruption of the <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> Act, though the liberty of it be declared a Fundamental Right; Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices upon Evidences, even to Blood by Promiſes and Threats, which are Boots and Bribes in the upright Senſe of this Government; the general Complaint of ſober Men, <hi>Scotch-men,</hi> of the Violation of the Conditions upon which they preſented the King with the Crown of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and the <hi>Wracking</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> there, againſt the Laws of that Kingdom, as well as of this; and, it is ſaid; by particular Orders from hence; laſt of all, the danger and ſcandal of our Adminiſtration in general, by the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of incompetent Perſons, ſuch as are ſuſpected of Falſeneſs, or that are of known Inſufficiency; as often as any free, or good Thing is propoſed, they oppoſe it in pretence of upholding the Monarchy; and, as with this, they flatter the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and weak Part of this King; ſo if he comes to fail, they recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves to King <hi>James,</hi> if he or his Son ſucceed, with the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of ſupporting the Crown againſt a Common-wealth: For theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I am lead to ſay, if this be the laſt opportunity for the King to be Victorious, it may be the laſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for us to be Free. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Princes wanted not good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and were acceſſible upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and extreamly Civil, as if they had a mind to live well with their People; but they had not Power to reſiſt the evil Influences of ſome Men about them. And though this King ſhews great Magnanimity in the Field, he is Conquered daily in the Cabinet; And by whom, pray, more than by him that in the worſt of Times was the worſt of Tools? and to the eternal Infamy of this Government, is endured at the head of Affairs in a War againſt <hi>France,</hi> that was by the Commons of <hi>England</hi> Impeached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Letters under his own Hand of a treacherous Negotiation with <hi>France;</hi> nor is this the blackeſt of his Crimes, and therefore not the groſeſt of our Follies to ſuffer him. His Capital Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is, at once, ſubverting the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the People of <hi>England.</hi> It is <hi>High Treaſon</hi> to invade the Royal Bed, by the Laws of this Kingdom; But what is it then, or ought it to be to an Houſe of Commons, to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe upon their Honour, to buy off the People's Repreſentatives, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Truſt, and turn them againſt themſelves? Next to them that took Money, he muſt be the worſt of Men. This is <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it is a diſſolving Fundamental Truſt, and legally enthrawling us; it is making the People, <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> to deſtroy themſelves. What Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo vile? What Proſtitution ſo ſcandalous? It is beyond Example, and it ſeems it is above Puniſhment, and he is uſed, and looks, and acts; as if he were Meritorious. Shall an Houſe of Commons endure this, and in a Government under the fair Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Reformation? As if we were reconci'ed to the Miniſtry and Meaſures, that were the Cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53772:3"/>this bold-Turn. This gives me all the Impreſſions of Grief and Pity, that with the Dog we ſhould return to our Vomit, and like Swine feed upon Excrements. We offer our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies the greateſt Advantages, while we let them ſee we can thus contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and give our ſelves the lye, and change our Minds of Men that are not changed; and can do any Thing to ſerve a turn, which makes the whole look Inſincere and a Trick; and if it were not Impious, to be ſure it were Unwiſe to do ſo.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Motives that preſs me, and which make me ſo free and earneſt with you, to value this laſt opportunity to all the Advantages, the great Wiſdom of this Houſe may draw thence, by a full Improvement of it. Let no reſpects divert you, as you will anſwer it to God and Man; I muſt be plain, it is a Bargain you muſt make for your All, make it ſure; the omiſſion ſeems to render it irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trievable. Let not ill Men and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, cover it ſelf under big Words againſt <hi>France.</hi> You know who cries ſtop Thief: Names ſhould not coſen you out of this happy Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, nor your Conduct ſhew you will be ever Prodigal of the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences that would ſave you. Take the King's Advice, apply it wiſely and quickly; he has been abroad, and has the Advantage of the <hi>Confederates</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, as well as his own, which we have Reaſon to believe is very Good; and upon the whole Matter tells us, as the laſt and moſt important Motive to us, That we have but this opportunity: Be ready therefore with your Money, but be ready with your Rights too; and as wiſe Parliaments have ever done, let them have the Preference. I don't bid you ask why <hi>Ireland</hi> was not ſooner reduced; why we had not above half as many Men as we have paid for, why Supplies were ſo long a going, and ſo many unneceſſary Ships for Tenders were chargeably continued, nor how much we are in Debt after the many Millions we have given, beſides thoſe the conſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue has yielded, ſome ſay, in all, above Fifteen; no, I will not be ſo ill natured or unreaſonable, not a word of mine ſhall look towards Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or Diſaffiction, but leave all this till laſt; if we Proſper it will be time enough: I would not hinder Supplies by no means, only get into Poſſeſſion of your antient Rights, your ſo much needed and eſſential Rights; and if it ſhould pleaſe God the King ſhould fail of his Hopes, or fall by his Enemies, you are in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, you have Ground to ſtand on worth defending, and that will ſecure you; for that it ſelf will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage and unite all Intereſts, becauſe their own is involved; we muſt not depend upon his Perſonal Succeſs, but our own Conſtitutions; every one will ſtand up heartily for that which is his. Convince the Kingdom they are the better for the Change, or their heat will ſoon cool in ſupporting it; let them ſee their Legiſlation and Adminiſtration are ſecure; the firſt by annual Parliaments without any Evaſion, and by free and genuine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, which cannot be without the Sheriffs are choſen by the County Courts, as the Coroners are, and that the Fines on them for falſe returns, and thoſe that ſit upon them be very heavy, and appropriated out of the reach of the Crown to remit, which will ſecure our Legiſlation; let Miniſters be impeachable, and the Parliament ſit till the Perſon accuſed be tried and acquitted, or puniſhed; and all ſuch Criminals be unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and irreprievable, but at their Requeſt: Provided always, That if any Miniſter be named, as Culpable by any Perſon in Parliament, he ſhall be obliged to make it good, or at leaſt be diſmiſs'd the Houſe, and made
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53772:4"/>uncapable of any Employment in the Government; and regulate Tryals, as to the liberty of the Priſoner, the number and qualification of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes as well as Juries, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that Bill which is depending; and hereby our Adminiſtration will be in a good degree ſecured alſo.</p>
            <p>I do further propoſe, That during this War a Committee of Lords and Commons be the Cabinet, and that they have the inſpection of Navy, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and Treaſury, and the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of all Officers employed in either Capacity, the Juncture calls for it. Were the King an Angel, he is not Omnipreſent no more than Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent; and if he wants your Power, he needs your Preſence, Judgement, and Direction; a Common-wealth requires a <hi>Dictator,</hi> but a Monarchy the <hi>People in Parliament</hi> upon great Emergencies. Remember he is a K. of your making, and he ſhould be one of your influencing, if not Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Over-ruling in ſuch Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as ours. Favour or Connivance in Government, is for eaſie and not difficult Times: Judge well and Act vigorouſly, but Act ſo as to ſave your Selves, your Countrey I mean, whether this or the other K. prevail; for be aſſured if we are in Poſſeſſion of our Rights, we are ſafe againſt this King's Victory, and King <hi>James</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, that neither ſhall hurt us; elſe you will find your ſelves expoſed to the ill Conſequence, that may follow one or t'other: Have a care of after Games, eſpecially now, when you are told you have but one opportunity for all. I cannot but urge that in your Ears, that you heard laſt from his Mouth, as the moſt preſſing Motive to his Supply. All good Men are in pain for you, and particularly what part you act in this Affair, and the ſucceſs it may have to the Felicity of the whole. God Almighty direct us, for all is at ſtake while both our Legiſlation and Adminiſtration are unſettled, and all will be ſafe to us if we are ſecure at home; for it is feared, and juſtly, I think, that as our Saviour ſaid, Our greateſt Enemies are of our own Houſe; our own Family, Men in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and in Government, let King <hi>James</hi>'s Fate be your Admonition; truſt your ſelves, and others ſhall not betray you; employ Men of Principles, of Skill, and Sobriety. For your Fleet you will find them better at <hi>Ratcliff-high-way,</hi> than at <hi>Lock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and the <hi>Blue-poſts.</hi> For the Army, mix, with ſome that you have, honeſt Countrey Gentlemen and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, that are both ſober and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And in every Commiſſion ſee that you have only ſuch Perſons, as were bred up in the Buſineſs of thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions they ſerve in; as in the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Merchants;</hi> in the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> thoſe that have been <hi>Brewers</hi> and have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it over; in the <hi>Admiralty, Navy,</hi> and <hi>Victualling Offices, Ancient Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> that have had good Commands, and known the providing of Stores for their own Ships; for whom theſe Employments ſhould be referved as honourable Retreats; and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the Government to the aged and experienced, for their former good Services; who, for one half of the Revenue that is now paid, would bleſs themſelves and you. Nor ſhould our Council, or Cabinet, be without a <hi>Seaman,</hi> a <hi>Souldier,</hi> a <hi>Merchant,</hi> a <hi>Civilian,</hi> a <hi>Common Lawyer,</hi> and ſome <hi>Countrey Gentlemen,</hi> and ſuch as have ſerved long and well in <hi>Embaſſies</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, which comprehends both Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick and Foreign, Civil and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Affairs. Remember that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and inſtructing Remarque of Sir <hi>William Temple,</hi> in his Account of <hi>Holland, That though the People in general, were not as quick and witty as their Neighbours, yet their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was generally wiſer, becauſe the wiſeſt of the People governed; they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53772:4"/>chooſe and prefer the ableſt, which for other Reſpects were advanced in Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Governments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would you be great or ſafe? Add to what we have ſaid, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of the Eſtabliſhment by Land and Sea in the <hi>Rump</hi>'s Time; obſerve by what Conduct ſo few, and moſt of them but of the middle ſort of Men, became the Admiration and Terror of the <hi>World.</hi> Send for <hi>H.</hi> that was Treaſurer of the Navy, and <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>D.</hi> that were Treaſurers for the Army in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and able Men, and alive, and you will ſee that our yearly Charge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds both that of the Civil War, and War with <hi>Holland</hi> too, when <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> had Armies to be paid, as well as <hi>Ireland.</hi> I ſay obſerve Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and judge; whatever is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ballance your greater Expences, is due to their better Conduct. Be not offended with me, but imitate and mend; the time invites us, and our Station obliges us to it, and the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant,</hi> I mean the King's <hi>Declaration,</hi> that <hi>Aſſociation</hi> for the Change; Shall it be waſte Paper under it? God forbid; call for it, Settle and Rule by it; to be ſure it is the <hi>Original Contract</hi> of our new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And unpardonable are they that after all our Blood and Treaſure ſpilt and ſpent, (and we know not where they will ſtop,) ſhall out of Fear or Flattery loſe the Advantages promis'd, for want of asking and preſſing the Performance. I muſt put you in mind of one of them before we part, and that was <hi>Sending back the Foreign Troops if you pleaſe;</hi> And wont you pleaſe ſince <hi>Ireland</hi> is redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? It is hoped you will; and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band our Engliſh ones too: What elſe are we the eaſier for <hi>Ireland's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reduced? Which we all ſuſpected was prolonged on purpoſe to have a pretence for Money; And will you continue the Charge even now, when they have not that pretence? Better Things are expected from you. I beg your Patience a little longer, we are an Iſland. <hi>A Navy is an Engliſh ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army.</hi> Add 10 or 20 Sail of Ships, if you pleaſe, to the Eſtabliſhment, but no more ſtanding Armies now, I beſeech you. Conquering of <hi>France,</hi> which ſome hot Heads Dream of, is not our Buſineſs, if it were in our Power; and therefore muſt be the paſſion of Fools and hope of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. It was never attempted but by <hi>Ed</hi> 3. and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> 5. Princes of great Minds and Sufficiency; but they rather ſhew'd <hi>France</hi> and the World what they could do, than what they could keep; and made the Experiment at the Expence of that Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that we were the worſe for our Glory, even while we could maintain it: But that failed us alſo at length, and we ever loſt all back again, with more Diſhonour than we got it with Reputation. We had need have the Spaniſh Mines, or the Philoſopher's Stone, and a <hi>Race of Black Princes,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Edwards</hi> and <hi>Henrys,</hi> to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſupport ſuch an Enterpriſe. <hi>France</hi> is Three times as big as <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and Populous and Rich in Proportion; the Revenue of the Crown is one Third of the yearly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the whole; the <hi>Clergy</hi> have another Third, and the <hi>Laity</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Third; of all which, the <hi>New Converts</hi> make not the Five hundredth Part, as they are not in Number the Two hundredth Man. Now if the French King hath more than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of all <hi>England</hi> to carry on his War, and a Clergy ſo Rich, and whom he has ſo much obliged to help him, and that will not let him want for ſo good a Cauſe, as they count this in favour of King <hi>James,</hi> that is an Exile for his and their Religion, beſides what his People can furniſh, zealous enough in their way, and very Bigots to him; to which vaſt Treaſure add
<pb facs="tcp:53772:5"/>his incomparable Conduct, in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Secrecy, and Diſpatch, ſuiting Men to Things, and both to Time and Place, with the Succeſſes we ſee have followed him every where, as if he had Fortune in his Power. It ſhews him to be a <hi>Match</hi> for all his Enemies, and that they muſt think of being Defenſive in their turn as well as he; and truly, <hi>If be beats us when he fights, and fights but when he pleaſes, he will beat us at laſt;</hi> and whatever we may fancy, <hi>France</hi> is Thrice more to us now, in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than what it was, which we do not or will not ſee, becauſe old Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings and preſent Heats coſen us. We are encreaſed in Trade and Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſo are they in Proportion, in Naval Affairs; in Revenue of the Crown; in Command and Diſcipline; they are Proportionably <hi>Five to One</hi> to what they were in <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. Time. It's true we might at firſt, with great Charge, have landed upon them and made ſome Confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, as we might have reduc'd <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſaved all this Blood and Treaſure, but private Reſpects tools place. However, that attempt upon <hi>France</hi> would have been too hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous for wiſe Men to make; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Repulſe that might have followed; our Navy— might have been Wind bound, Proviſions thereby wanted, and the Charge of an Army and Navy at firſt, would have come too faſt, and been too much for the People to have underſtood; and if it had not ſucceeded to our mighty Hopes, it would have been a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Slur upon the King, from whom ſome expected not ſo much as they have ſeen, and others a great deal more. Laying aſide the Vanity of Conqueſts abroad, it will become us to have a care of them at home; that while we think of nothing leſs than Freeing or Poſſeſſing other Countreys, we may not <hi>Inſenſibly loſe or enſlave our own.</hi> We have land enough, and a free Government, if we might injoy it. Our part is little more than Defenſive; ſcower the Coaſt and you ſecure the Iſland and the Trade, which is the Life of it: But if after <hi>Fifteen Millions</hi> of Mony already paid in Three years, (which, by the way, has not been known ſince the <hi>Norman Dukes,</hi> which is now above 600 years agoe,) you will give more without ſetling the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and changeing Hands, and thereby purging the Adminiſtration, <hi>We are an undone as well as a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous People.</hi> The <hi>Army</hi> the King asks is for the <hi>Continent,</hi> and not an <hi>Iſland,</hi> And what have we to do there? Is not our <hi>Quota</hi> enough? Are any but the <hi>Dutch</hi> concerned in the Charge at <hi>Sea?</hi> And of that do we not bear a double Share? Beſides, Have any of the <hi>Confederacy</hi> aſſiſted us in the reducing of <hi>Ireland?</hi> Let us obſerve Proportion. But that which is both our ſurpriſe and trouble, is to find that his Majeſty tells us of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears,</hi> after all that has been given, when it is made plain to us, that though we did the laſt year Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Supplies to 70000 Men, there never were 50 of them in pay: Pray let that <hi>Overplus</hi> be applied to the <hi>Arrears,</hi> or thoſe that received it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to refund to the Publick— We do not ſee to the end of our Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and cannot be too good Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands for the People that pay it, who though they are and will be very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, have often proved they are not made for Burthen. I will ſay no more to Perſons of your <hi>Talents;</hi> nor had I ſaid ſo much but to Men of your <hi>Stations.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
